Guide to the Journalism Department Photographs 1930-1984
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
Journalism Department Photographs
1930-1984
1970-1984
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center University Archives 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
P 208
Oregon State University. Dept. of Journalism.
0.4 cubic feet, including 105 photographs 3 boxes, including 2 oversize boxes
The Journalism Department Photographs consist of images created or acquired by Journalism Department staff for use in publications and displays as well as photographs taken and mounted by students for class projects. Subject include student activities, campus buildings, and Oregon scenic views.
Historical Note:
Journalism courses were first offered at Oregon Agricultural College during the 1914/15 school year, and the Department of Industrial Journalism was created in 1918. The department's purpose was to train students "who wish to take positions on farm and trade journals, newspapers, and other publications, especially where writing on industrial subjects such as Agriculture, Home Economics, and Engineering is required" (1919/20 OAC Catalogue). On three occasions during the 1920s, the State Board of Higher Curricula was requested to consider restricting or eliminating industrial journalism at Oregon State. During the 1930s and 1940s, journalism at Oregon State was administered jointly with the program at the University of Oregon as part of the higher education reorganization in Oregon. In 1969, departmental majors were offered for the first time; subsequently, thirty technical minors were added. In 1992, the Journalism Department was eliminated as part of university wide budget reductions.
The Journalism Department Photographs consist of images created or assembled by Journalism Department staff and students. All of the images are b/w prints. Subjects depicted in the photographs include the members and activities of the Sigma Delta Chi journalism honorary society at Oregon State; students and student activities; campus buildings, including the Library and LaSells Stewart Center; the sculpture on Jefferson Street south of the library; and Oregon scenes. Of especial note are images of Journalism Department faculty, Fred Shideler and John Burtner, and graduates, Tom Eggers and Shawn Church.
The images in Series IV through VI of student activities, campus buildings, and Oregon scenes may have been assembled by the department in preparing publicity for the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication annual conference held in Corvallis in 1983. Several of the images are available online and are linked from the item descriptions.
Photographers are indicated for many of the images and include Allan J. de Lay, Ed Hershberger, and the Oregon Department of Transportation.
Collection is open for research.
Arranged in 7 series: I. Sigma Delta Chi, 1930-1939; II. Beaver Boys State, circa 1960; III. Journalism Graduates, 1983-1984; IV. Campus Buildings, circa 1976-1983; V. Student Activities and Academic Programs, 1978-1980; VI. Oregon Views, circa 1980; and VII. Student Projects, circa 1970s.
Transferred in two accessions in 1995 and 1996 from University Publications and Student Media.
The Journalism Department Records (RG 091) document the technical journalism curriculum at Oregon State and the administration of the department. Additional photographs of Journalism Department faculty and programs are part of the Gwil Evans Photographic Collection (P082:073).
Burtner, John C. (John Cole), 1895-; Shideler, Fred Merle.; De Lay, Allan J.; Hershberger, Ed.
Oregon State College--Faculty.; Oregon State College--Students.; Oregon State University--Buildings.; Oregon State University--Students.; Sigma Delta Chi. Oregon State Chapter.; Oregon. Dept. of Transportation.; Oregon State College. Dept. of Journalism.
College buildings--Oregon--Corvallis.; College students--Oregon--Corvallis.; Journalism--Study and teaching (Higher)--Oregon--Corvallis.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.
Photographic prints.
Colleges and Universities; Journalism; Sports and Recreation; Student Life; Oregon; Corvallis; Photographs
- Sigma Delta Chi, 1930-1939; Series I
  The Sigma Delta Chi photographs depict the members and activities of this journalism organization during the 1930s. Several of the photographs were published in the Beaver yearbook. Descriptions for these images were taken from the captions attached to the photographs.
  - Initiation, circa 1930; P208:01 (Box 1)
    Initiation with 6 men wearing straw hats and carrying parasols.
  - Barometer Bust, undated; P208:02 (Box 1)
    The annual Barometer Bust, sponsored by Sigma Delta Chi, is scheduled every spring. All members of the staffs of the Barometer, student daily paper, attend and are amused by the antics of Sigma Delta Chi members and prospective pledges. A future SDX member loses his pants as faculty members laugh in the background.
  - Dick Kennedy and Fred M. Shideler, undated; P208:03 (Box 1)
    Sigma Delta Chi Dick Kennedy, editor of the student daily, and Fred M. Shideler, head of Journalism Department and alumni member of SDX tap out stories at the downtown editorial offices of the student daily.
  - Publications Committee, 1938; P208:04 (Box 1)
    The Publications Committee of Oregon State College controls all student publications and selects the editors and managers of each one. Member of Sigma Delta Shi predominate on the committee shown above. At the extreme right is E.T. Reed, publications editor for the college and an associate member of Sigma Delta Chi. Seated at the head of the table and third from the right is Fred M. Shideler, head of the Journalism Department, Chairman of the Committee, and an alumni member of Sigma Delta Chi. Burch Davis, fourth from right and Ed Burchell, left are both member of the Oregon State chapter. Published in 1938 Beaver, p. 117.
  - Memorial Union, undated; P208:05 (Box 1)
    The Memorial Union building on the Oregon State College campus. This student-erected building houses the offices of all publications and the Journalism Department. Sigma Delta Chi is honored by being one of all publications and the Journalism Department. Sigma Delta Chi is honored by being one of the three honor or professional societies who have their own rooms in the building
  - John C. Burtner, 1939; P208:06 (Box 1)
    Chapter adviser John C. Burtner spreads it on at the annual Barometer Bust, funfest and party sponsored by Sigma Delta Chi for all students enrolled in journalism or working on the staff of a major publication on the campus. Published in the 1939 Beaver, p. 121.
  - Student Directory editors, 1938; P208:07 (Box 1)
    This group under the guidance of Hal Higgs, Sigma Delta Chi man shown in front center, edits the campus Student Directory, telephone book showing home addresses, school addresses, and school registered. Published in 1938 Beaver, p. 127.
  - SDX banquet, undated; P208:08 (Box 1)
    Part of the "festive board" at the SDX banquet honoring Dr. Rex Harlow, director of the Stanford School Press Relations Investigation, who is made an associate member of the OSC chapter last April. Dick Gearhart, president of the chapter and last year's delegate is shown on the extreme right.
  - SDX banquet and initiation, undated; P208:09 (Box 1)
    C.D. Byrne, director of information for the Oregon State System of Higher Education and a member of the Wisconsin chapter of SDX, takes a bite of ice cream between words with Dr. Rex. F. Harlow, professor of education at Stanford University and director of the Stanford School Press Relations Investigation. Dick Kennedy, editor of the Daily Barometer, is on Dr. Harlow's left. The banquet followed Dr. Harlow's initiation as an associate member of the OSC chapter.
  - SDX professional meeting, 1938; P208:10 (Box 1)
    Ben Ames, famed United Press European correspondent, was the center of interest at one of the Oregon State SDX professional meetings last spring. A number of the campus "big shots" including President George W. Peavy (standing) came in for the luncheon meeting. Ames is shown in the center, thumb in vest. Published in the 1938 Beaver, p. 240.
  - SDX professional meeting, undated; P208:11 (Box 1)
    Another view of the Ben Ames professional meeting, showing Ames (fourth from the left) with President Peavy, Dr. U.G. Dubach, Dean of Men; the Japanese consul from Portland; and W.A. Jensen, executive secretary of the college, following in order. Ames gave one of the most interesting talks and brought forth more questions than perhaps any other person who addressed the SDX men during the year.
  - Hall Higgs, Student Directory Editor, 1938; P208:12 (Box 1)
    Sigma Delta Chi is a co-sponsor of the Student Directory. Here, Editor Hall Higgs directs the activities of the staff from the Barometer workroom. Published in 1938 Beaver, p. 127.
- Beaver Boys State, circa 1960; Series II
  - Assembly on patio roof of Weatherford Dining Hall; b/w contact sheet., undated; P208:13 (Box 1)
- Journalism Graduates, 1983-1984; Series III
  - Tom Eggers, graduated in 1984, P208:14 (Box 1)
  - Shawn Church, graduated in 1983, P208:15 (Box 1)
- Campus Buildings, circa 1976-1983; Series IV
  The campus buildings photographs include images of the Kerr Administration Building, Benton Hall, the Memorial Union, Waldo Hall, LaSells Strewart Center, and campus dormitories.
  - Administrative Services Building, P208:16 (Box 1)
  - Benton Hall, P208:17-P208:20
    - April 7, 1976, P208:17-P208:18; Allan J. de Lay, photographer. (Box 1)
  - Memorial Union, undated; P208:21-P208:25
    - Exterior, P208:21-P208:24 (Box 1)
    - Memorial Union Lounge, P208:25 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Union East, circa 1981; P208:26 (Box 1)
  - Waldo Hall, P208:27 (Box 1)
  - Library, P208:28-P208:31
    - May 8, 1978, P208:28; Allan J. de Lay, photographer. (Box 1)
    - Sculpture at Jefferson Street (south) Entrance, P208:30 (Box 1)
    - View of Sculpture and Jefferson Street, circa 1981; P208:31 (Box 1)
  - Dormitories, P208:32-P208:34
    - Finley Hall, P208:32 (Box 1)
    - Bloss and Finley Halls, P208:33 (Box 1)
    - Callahan Hall, P208:34 (Box 1)
  - Farrier School, P208:35 (Box 1)
  - LaSells Stewart Center, P208:36-P208:46
    - Exterior, P208:36-P208:40 (Box 1)
    - Patio, P208:41; Ed Hershberger, photographer. (Box 1)
    - Exterior, P208:42; Ed Hershberger, photographer. (Box 1)
    - Guistina Gallery, P208:43; Ed Hershberger, photographer. (Box 1)
    - Austin Auditorium, P208:44-P208:45; Ed Hershberger, photographer. (Box 1)
    - Interior, Guistina Gallery, P208:46 (Box 1)
- Student Activities and Academic Programs, 1978-1980; Series V
  - Marching band, close-up of trombones, P208:47; Photo by Robert DeGiulio. (Box 1)
  - Forestry student logroll, P208:48 (Box 1)
  - Wecoma research vessel, P208:49 (Box 1)
  - Student identifies vital parts of a rodent, 1978; P208:50 (Box 1)
    Published in 1978 Beaver, p. 245.
  - Sea Grant College Program; researcher studies crabs, P208:51 (Box 1)
  - Student with fish net in waist-deep water, P208:52 (Box 1)
- Oregon Views, circa 1980; Series VI
  These b/w prints depict various scenic views of the Oregon coast, Columbia Gorge, Cascades, and central Oregon. All images provided by the Oregon Department of Transportation.
  - View of Marys Peak from Kings Valley, P208:53 (Box 1)
  - Sunset Bay, P208:54 (Box 1)
  - Cape Perpetua, P208:55 (Box 1)
  - Otter Rock, P208:56 (Box 1)
  - Samuel H. Boardman State Park, north of Brookings, P208:57 (Box 1)
  - Tillamook Bay, P208:58 (Box 1)
  - Tillamook Head, P208:59 (Box 1)
  - Cape Kiwanda, P208:60 (Box 1)
  - View from Cape Arago, P208:61 (Box 1)
  - Beach south of Brandon, P208:62 (Box 1)
  - Seal Rock, P208:63 (Box 1)
  - Beverly Beach with Yaquina Lighthouse in Background, P208:64 (Box 1)
  - Heceta Head Lighthouse, P208:65 (Box 1)
  - Beach south of Cannon Beach, P208:66 (Box 1)
  - Crater Lake, P208:67 (Box 1)
  - Reflection of Mount Hood in Lost Lake, P208:68 (Box 1)
  - Mount Hood and Lost Lake, P208:69 (Box 1)
  - Mount Hood and Hood River Valley, P208:70 (Box 1)
  - Orchards in bloom in Hood River Valley, P208:71 (Box 1)
  - Lower Columbia River near Astoria, P208:72 (Box 1)
  - Cape Kiwanda, P208:73 (Box 1)
  - Columbia River Gorge with Vista House on Crown Point, P208:74 (Box 1)
  - Mount Jefferson and Metolius River, P208:75 (Box 1)
  - Smith Rock with Mount Jefferson in background, P208:76 (Box 1)
  - Black Butte Ranch Golf Course with Mount Washington in background, P208:77 (Box 1)
  - Trail of the Molten Land near Lava Lands Visitor Center, south of Bend, P208:78 (Box 1)
  - Smith Rock, P208:79 (Box 1)
  - Smith Rock (?), P208:80 (Box 1)
- Student Projects, circa 1970s; Series VII
  Series VII consists of photographs taken and mounted by students for Journalism Department class projects.
  - Fountain on Jefferson Street side of library, 1971 (Box 2)
    Anonymous photographer.
  - Karl Moltmann and the Madrigal Singers rehearsing in Benton Hall, circa 1970; 6 images (Box 2)
    Greg Collin, photographer.
  - Portrait of a young woman, 1971 (Box 2)
    Jon Gray, photographer.
  - So who needs a desk?, circa 1970; 6 images (Box 2)
    Students studying on lawn, in library, in Memorial Union lounge, and elsewhere. Chris Bunsen, photographer.
  - Willamette Valley agricultural land with Marys Peak in background, 1971 (Box 2)
    Michael J. Myers, photographer.
  - Man running on track (intramurals?), circa 1970s (Box 2)
  - Women holding candlelight vigil, circa 1970; 5 images (Box 2)
    Rick Packard, photographer.
  - Greek living, circa 1975; 6 images (Box 3)
    Fraternity activities including intramurals; IFC sing; volleyball; cleaning train in Avery Park; sweeping porch of Delta Tau Delta house; and a meal. Don Mason, photographer.
  - Rugby match, circa 1975; 6 images (Box 3)
    Herman Jottman (sp?), photographer.